At some point, these behaviors are fostered by a culture that promotes individual gain over collective progress. So if we're going to uproot corruption, we have got to start before it ever takes root. We have got to intervene early. I don't know about your country, but where I come from, youth will lead us into the future. In Kenya today, 80 percent of the population is under the age of 35. But by their own admission, they have conflicting values. Fifty-eight percent of young people in Kenya recently told us they will do anything to make money. An additional 45 percent said corruption is a legitimate tool for doing business. Seventy-three percent said they would not be willing to stand up for what they believe in for fear of retribution. What I learned from my mother a few years ago was this concept of "the power of one" -- that each of us can be potent agents of change and that together, we are a force, that if we put our hands together, we can change the situation and no problem is too big. My mother understood this so profoundly that it was at the center of her work. Shifting cultures takes patience, persistence and commitment, and it is extremely slow and deep work. But if we are going to shift a culture, we have got to get that work started. And in the time since her passing, we have established a foundation in her name to do exactly that but to work with young people and children to begin to build character and personal leadership, to inspire purpose and integrity. But fighting corruption is not as easy as saying corruption is bad. Now, here are three strategies that we are employing that we believe can be replicated in any school community. First, we must understand the why: Why does corruption happen in the first place? Do we call it for what it is -- theft -- or do we gloss over it with other words? When young children are able to model what it looks and feels like to deal with corruption, they are likely, when faced with a dilemma in their future, to model what they've been taught. Second, we need to teach character explicitly. Now, this may seem obvious, but a child who exhibits a growth mindset and a sense of self-control is self-confident. And a self-confident child is likely to stand up for what they believe. Third, we need to build personal leadership in our children early to give them an opportunity to know what it looks like to call corruption out when they see it, what it feels like to stand up and be counted when they're needed and, for me, to make the more and most important connection between human suffering on one hand and corruption, greed and selfishness on the other. We have got to believe in our capacity to bring about the future we want to see, each of us in our small way. Young people must believe that a new reality is possible. Corruption, climate change, ecosystem collapse, biodiversity loss -- all these issues need leadership. And in the words of Baba Dioum of Senegal, "In the final analysis, we will conserve only what we love, we will love only what we understand and we will understand only what we are taught." Thank you. (Applause)
En algún momento, esas conductas son potenciadas por una cultura que promueve el beneficio personal sobre el beneficio colectivo. Por lo tanto, si elegimos desplazar la corrupción, debemos comenzar antes de que se arraigue. Debemos intervenir temprano. No sé qué es lo que sucede en sus países pero en el mío la juventud nos liderará hacia el futuro. Hoy en día en Kenia, el 80 % de la población es menor de 35 años. Pero, según ellos, tienen valores opuestos. El 58 % de los jóvenes de Kenia dijo recientemente que haría cualquier cosa para ganar dinero. El 45 % dijo que la corrupción es una herramienta legítima para hacer negocios. El 73 % dijo que no está dispuesto a defender lo que cree por miedo a un posible castigo. Lo que aprendí gracias a mi madre hace unos años es acerca del "poder que tiene cada individuo", que cada uno de nosotros puede ser un agente potencial del cambio y que, juntos, somos una fuerza, que si nos unimos, podemos cambiar la situación y ningún problema resulta irresoluble. Mi madre entendía esto de manera tan profunda que era el centro de su labor. Cambiar una cultura requiere paciencia, perseverancia y compromiso, y es una tarea muy lenta y profunda. Pero si queremos cambiar una cultura debemos comenzar a trabajar. Y, luego de que mi madre falleciera, creamos una fundación en su nombre para hacer exactamente eso pero trabajamos con jóvenes y niños para empezar a construir el carácter y el liderazgo personal para infundir determinación e integridad. Pero combatir a la corrupción no es tan fácil como decir que la corrupción es mala. Bien, tenemos tres estrategias que estamos implementando y que creemos que pueden ser implementadas en cualquier comunidad educativa. Primero, debemos comprender el porqué: ¿Por qué la corrupción existe en primer lugar? ¿La llamamos por lo que es -un robo- o la encubrimos con otras palabras? Cuando los niños sepan cómo se ve y cómo se siente lidiar con la corrupción, probablemente, cuando enfrenten un dilema en el futuro, lidien con ello de la manera que se les haya enseñado. En segundo lugar, debemos enseñar explícitamente a crear un carácter. Bien, esto debe parecer obvio pero un niño que demuestra una mentalidad de crecimiento y autocontrol es seguro de sí mismo. Y un niño seguro de sí mismo probablemente defienda sus convicciones. En tercer lugar, tenemos que construir el liderazgo personal temprano para enseñarles cómo desafiar a la corrupción cuando estén ante ella, cómo se siente defenderse y ser tenido en cuenta y, para mí, establecer la conexión más importante entre el sufrimiento humano por un lado y, por el otro, la corrupción, la avaricia y el egoísmo. Debemos creer en nuestra capacidad para crear el futuro que deseamos; cada uno de nosotros puede aportar su grano de arena. Los jóvenes deben creer en la posibilidad de una nueva realidad. La corrupción, el cambio climático, el colapso del ecosistema, la pérdida de biodiversidad -- todas estas cuestiones requieren una dirección -- Y en palabras de Baba Dioum, de Senegal: "Al final, conservaremos solo lo que amemos, amaremos solo lo que entendamos y entenderemos solo lo que se nos enseñe". Gracias. (Aplausos)